<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paper called the Agreement of the people taken into consideration, and the lawfulness of subscription to it examined, and resolved in the negative, by the ministers of Christ in the province of Lancaster. Published by them especially for the satisfaction of the conscience, and guiding of the practise of our entirely honored and beloved, the people of our several churches, committed to our charge; and for the general good of this Church &amp; nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E546_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863194</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863194</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E546[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paper called the Agreement of the people taken into consideration, and the lawfulness of subscription to it examined, and resolved in the negative, by the ministers of Christ in the province of Lancaster. Published by them especially for the satisfaction of the conscience, and guiding of the practise of our entirely honored and beloved, the people of our several churches, committed to our charge; and for the general good of this Church &amp; nation.</title>
                  <author>Heyrick, Richard, 1600-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24, 33-36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Luke Fawne, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Parrot in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Richard Heyrick [and 53 other ministers].</note>
                  <note>A reply to: An agreement prepared for the people of England and the places therewith incorporated, for a secure and present peace, upon grounds of common right, freedom and safety.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 26 1648".</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages 25-32 of "The subject's sorrovv or lamentations vpon the death of Britaines Iosiah, King Charles" erroneously bound in between p. 24 and p. 33. The beginning of "The subject's sorrow" is at reel 84:E.546[16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Foundations of freedom.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE PAPER Called the <hi>AGREEMENT of the PEOPLE</hi> taken into CONSIDERATION, AND The Lawfulneſs of Subſcription to it Examined, and Reſolved in the Negative, by the Miniſters of Chriſt in the PROVINCE of LANCASTER.</p>
                  <p>Publiſhed by them eſpecially for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Conſcience, and guiding of the practiſe of our entirely honored and beloved, the People of our ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, committed to our Charge; and for the general good of this Church &amp; Nation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for LUKE FAWNE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the <hi>Parrot</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1649.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115380:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115380:2"/>
                  <head>The paper called the Agreement of the People taken into Conſideration, and the lawfulneſs of Subſcription to it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and reſolved in the negative, by the Miniſters of Chriſt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>LANCASTER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Agreement being drawn up in the name <hi>of the People of England,</hi> and by the Title of the Book being <hi>tendered to the Conſideration of the People,</hi> as alſo by a <hi>Declaration,</hi> bearing the name of <hi>his Excellency</hi> THOMAS <hi>Lord</hi> FAIRFAX, <hi>and his general Councel of Officers,</hi> annexed to it, it is ſaid to be <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the People of England;</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Declaration deſiring that all good people of England Will cordially embrace it, and by Subſcription declare their Concurrence, and accord thereto, when it ſhall be tendered to them, as is directed therein:</hi> And it being of univerſal Concernment, taking in, and deſpoſing of all publique Affairs, not onely of the <hi>Civil State,</hi> but of <hi>Religion:</hi> We the <hi>Ministers of Christ</hi> in the <hi>Province of Lancaster,</hi> who have conſtantly and cordially adhered to the Cauſe of <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> both in the firſt and ſecond War, and have oppoſed, according to our places and Callings, the late Scottiſh Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (by which many of us have been Sufferers,) and (having
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115380:3"/>been called thereunto by the Authority of Parliament) have not only taken, but preſs'd upon our people both <hi>the Vow and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi> to 5 May, 1641. and the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> in the latter of which we have bound our ſelves, Art. 6. <hi>in the Cauſe therein Covenanted, all the days of our lives zealouſly and constantly to continue against all Oppoſition, and to promote the ſame, according to our power, against all Lets and Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever; and what we are not able our ſelves to ſuppreſs or overcome, to reveal, and make known, that it may be timely prevented or removed.</hi> And <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>That we ſhall alſo, with all faithfulneſs, endeavor the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been or ſhall be Incendiaries, Malignants, or evil Instruments, by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Reformation of Religion, dividing the King from his People, or one of the Kingdoms from another, or making any faction or parties amongst the People, contrary to this League and Covenant;</hi> do hold our ſelves bound (our common intereſt, and relations, our ſpecial vocations, and our aforeſaid Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being conſidered) not only deliberately to weigh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, with our ſelves and one another, what to do in reference to this Agreement, but publiquely to make known our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning it, for the reſolution of thoſe that may be in doubt about it, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t thoſe that are for it may have our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why we diſſent from it; and we humbly and dearly entreat our highly honored and beloved Country-men and Brethren of this Kingdom, into whoſe hand this our paper may come; as well the Compoſers and Publiſhers of the Agreement, as thoſe to whom it is directed and intended, to be offered for their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, more eſpecially the Inhabitants of this County, unto whom we ſtand in a more intimate relation, both as living among, and having the ſpiritual Charge reſpectively of them, candidly to take and interpret, and conſcientiouſly to perpend this our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely conceived, and ſetled Judgment.</p>
                  <p>This Draught, called the Agreement of the People, being a Platform of State-Government, calculated for this Nation, and ſo, more immediately of a Political or Civil Conſideration; Our undertaking is not to ſurvey, or give our Verdict on every thing it holds forth diviſively, or by diſtinct Sections, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yee ſhall we examine any thing in it Politically, or by the rule of State-M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, or the Laws of the Realm, we remit that work to the learned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115380:3"/>State-men and Lawyers of the Land<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aſhurſts</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c. and Mr <hi>Prynnes</hi> Speech.</note>: But we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it as Chriſtians and Miniſters, enquiring and determining accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Talent how it may ſtand or diſagree with the dictates of Conſcience regulated by the Word of God: And in doing this, our method will be. 1. To give an account of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions upon the whole plot or frame taken together. 2. To ſpeak diſtinctly and particularly to the Ninth Section, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth Religion; whereupon we ſhall be the rather particular, becauſe it is both more proper to our profeſſion, and more preſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſouls.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt; The project of this Agreement is to place a power in the People, to alter when they will the Government of the Kingdom, to abrogate the preſent, and to erect a new form of Policy, and to be Lords paramount, or tranſcendental Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators over thoſe to whom the Government is committed, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to deliver them their Authority, to give them Laws, to diſanul the Laws they make, to conſine their Legiſlative power, and to oppoſe them by force of Arms when they ſee good; and to move them now to exert the ſaid power. This may appear by the whole tenor of the Agreement, and namely in that it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the People <hi>ordering the preſent Parliament to diſſolve</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 8 par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 1.</note>, appointing <hi>new Repreſentatives of a new</hi> proportion and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, (both in regard of places and perſons electing,) and of the manner, times, and other circumſtances of Election<note n="b" place="margin">Pag 8 par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 2. &amp;c.</note>, <hi>which are to have the ſupream truſt in order to the preſervation and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole, and their power is to extend without the conſent or concurrence of any other perſon or perſons, to the erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and aboliſhing of Courts of Juſtice, and publique Offices, and to the enacting, altering, repealing, and declaring of Laws, and the highest and final Judgment, concerning all natural or civil things</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Pa. 24. part. 8</note>, limiting the ſaid Repreſentatives from having power in many things<note n="d" place="margin">Pa. 24. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 8. &amp;c.</note>, directing and reſtraining them in matter of Religion<note n="e" place="margin">Pa. 26. par. 9</note>, and repealing all Laws. Ordinances, and Statutes, contrary to the Liberty in Religion which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide<note n="f" place="margin">Pa. 27 part 4</note>, reſerving in themſelves, or any of them, power to reſiſt them by force of Arms in ſome caſes<note n="g" place="margin">P. 27. part. 10</note>; And that ſuch a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental change was in the Intentions of the Compilers, is evident by the Declaration following it, which ſaith, <hi>it contains the beſt and most hopeful Foundations for the Peace and future well-Government
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115380:4"/>Government of this Nation</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Page 30.</note>, and in it they diſclaim to <hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in any thing, ſave the Fundamental ſetling of that power (to wit, the Law-giving, or Judicial power over the Kingdom) in the moſt equal and hopeful way for common Right, Freedom, and Safety, as in this Agreement</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Page 32.</note>.</p>
                  <p>This Agreement then perſwades the people to caſt off, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the preſent Government, to turn themſelves into an Anarchy, or jumbled multitude, to become a people without diſtinction or order, to run themſelves into that confuſion which the Jews were brought unto by the <hi>Babylonian Captivity,</hi> to be <hi>as the fiſhes of the ſea, as the creeping things that have no ruler over them</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Habak. 1.14.</note>, and ſo fit for nothing but to be angled by them that deſire to fiſh in troubled waters, for ſo it follows in the Text, <hi>they take up all of them with the angle, they catch them in their net, and gather them in their drags,</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> as though we were a colony, or company of men, ſwarmed or broken out from ſome other Nation, and newly landed in this Iſland, free and ready to elect and ſet up a frame of a Common-wealth, ſuch as we ſhould like beſt. Unto all this we ſay;</p>
                  <p>1. We are conſtituted Kingdom, a ſetled State, and under a lawful Government, which is very ancient, fully underſtood both by Magiſtrates and People, and deeply rooted in mens affections, both by long habituated exerciſe, and the well-approved benefices of it.</p>
                  <p>2. The Government we are under is good, wholeſom, equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Conſtitution of it, fitly ballanced and proportioned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reduced to the golden-mean, lying between Monarchical Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and Popular Anarchy, it hath had the general ſufferage to be one of the moderateſt and beſt tempered Governments in <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. The form of Government which we have are bound to own and continue under, not only by the ſingle tye of the duty of Subjects, but by ſacred obligation of <hi>Oaths, Vows and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> into which we have been called be called by lawful authority, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing or propounding them to us; as namely, 1. The Oath of Allegiance, in which the Subject ſolemnly ſweareth in theſe words, <hi>I ſhall bear faith and true allegiance to his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and him, and them, will defend to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of my power, againſt all conſpiracies and attempts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115380:4"/>which ſhall be made againſt his or their perſons, their Crown or Dignity,</hi> 2. The Oath of the Kings Supremacy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are theſe words, <hi>I do promiſe, that from henceforth I ſhall bear faith and true, allegiance to the Kings Highneſs, his Heirs, and lawful Succeſſors, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and defend all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, Priviledges, Preeminencies and Authorities granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſs, his Heirs, and Succeſſors, or united to the imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> 3. The Vow and and Proteſtation of 5 <hi>May,</hi> 1641. in which who ſo entreth into it, bindeth himſelf thus, <hi>I do in the preſence of Almighty God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, vow and protest to maintain and defend, as far as lawfully I may, with my life, power and eſtate, according to the duty of my Allegiance, his Majeſties, Royal Perſon, Honor and Eſtate, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Power and Priviledges, of Parliament, the lawful Rights and Liberties of the Subject, &amp;c.</hi> 4. And laſtly, The Solemn League and Covenant, wherein we with hands lifted up to the moſt high God to ſwear thus, <hi>We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reallity and conſtancy, in our ſeveral Vocations, endeavor with our eſtates and lives, mutually, to preſerve the Rights, and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdom, and to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon and Authority, in the Preſervation and defence of the true Religion, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdoms, that the world may bear witneſs with our Conſciences of our Loyalty, and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh his Majeſties juſt power or greatneſs.</hi> And it deſerves to be remembred, that the Parliament, at their entring into the Vow and Proteſtation, did it upon and apprehenſion, that our Government was in danger of undermining, and laid down their ſenſe thereof as one ſpecial ground of making the ſame,<note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>In the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble,</hi> and finding alſo that there have been, &amp; having just cauſe to ſuſpect that there ſtill are, even during the ſitting in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to ſubvert the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to introduce the exerciſe of an Arbitrary and Tyrannical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by moſt pernicious and wicked councels, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, plots and conſpiracies &amp;c.</note> and both entered and led the people into it expreſly for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of ſuch a deſign, adding to the tye of civil duty, the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bond of this Vow and Proteſtation, for the firmer obliging of our allegiance to the Government: And in the inſtructions for the taking of the Solemn League and Covenant throughout the Kingdom, <hi>Art.</hi> 10. there is an Exhortation ordered to be made to all ſorts of perſons to take it, <hi>as that which they judg not only lawful, but (all things conſidered) exceeding expedient, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for all that wiſh well to Religion, the King and Kingdom to joyn in.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115380:5"/>
                  <p>From theſe three Conſiderations, as Premiſes, we infer: Firſt, There's no place, need or occaſion for ſuch an attempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is the aboliſhing of the old, and rearing a new model of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>1. Say, that ſome inveſted with the Government have been faulty, that's no ground for changing the Government, if it be, we may run through all forms of policy, and ſtay in none, but ſtill be changing, for men will ſtill be found failing; our Government being lawful and good, our courſe is (as to this caſe) to pray that our Magiſtrates may be good, as we are required by the Apoſtle<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Tim. 2 1.2</note>, for unleſs it pleaſe God to give us juſt and godly Magiſtrates, the beſt Conſtitution will nothing avail us, and if that were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that which we have would ſerve our turn.</p>
                  <p>2. Say, that ſuch deep wounds have been given lately to our Government in the perſons of thoſe in which it was inherent, as that the influence of it into the body politique may be for a time ſuſpended, yet we cannot think that the Kingdom it ſelf is thereby beheaded of its Government, if that Maxime we have often heard of <hi>[The King never dyes]</hi> be true, and that Act for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Parliament, till it diſſolve it ſelf, be ſtill a Law, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but conceive we have a Government actually inveſted, and however it is, who can deny but ſtill there is an obligation and right in us to the Government? And as it is a far eaſier way to reſtore the former Government to its natural courſe, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, and ſettle another; ſo we beleeve, if we of this Nation ſhall find favour in the eyes of the Lord, he will raiſe it up again. We obſerve (if we underſtand the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp;c. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 20. and the <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 30. and the humble Anſwer of <hi>January</hi> 3. and the Petition before this Agreement,) that the late proceedings againſt thoſe in the ſeat of Authority were aſſerted, and put on as neceſſary, in order to the matter of this Agreement, and if ſo, the ſaid matter cannot be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by vertue of thoſe proceedings; deſperate and ſucceſſive things cannot really and innocently make each other neceſſary. And indeed until the compoſers of this Agreement prove the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental change of Goverment in it ſimply neceſſary, (which hitherto they have not (that we know of) aſſayed to do) the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of neceſſity for the aforeſaid proceedings, ſo far as it was built upon their tendency to this end, ſtands unſupported, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115380:5"/>we the rather point at, for that in the humble Anſwer aforeſaid we find acknowledged; <hi>That the late proceedings againſt the Parliament Members was a courſe in it ſelf-irregular, and not juſtifiable, but both by honeſt intentions for publique good, and an extraordinary neceſſity for the ſame end leading thereunto.</hi> Now if the changes in this Agreement be that end, and publique good, and they prove not at all neceſſary, (no not lawful, as we hope to manifeſt) the extraordinary neceſſity pretended thence for theſe proceedings vaniſheth into nothing. All that is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſaid for the needfulneſs of any thing in this Agreement, that we have met with, is layd down, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. <hi>Since therefore our former oppreſſions, and not yet ended troubles, have been occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, either by want of frequent National Meetings in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or by the undue on unequal Conſtitution thereof, or by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thoſe Meetings ineffectual, We are fully agreed, &amp;c.</hi> But the ſuperſtructure that follows upon this reaſon (to wit the change of Government) is too large fot this Foundation, the proviſions do far out-reach the grievances, which might eaſily (yea and we think only) be remedied, the Government ſtanding as it doth, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the two of thoſe three evils which are (to our thoughts) important, the diſ-continuance and ineffectualneſs of Parliaments, and for the former already proviſion hath been, made ſince this Parliament, and no doubt what remains neceſſary to be done againſt any of thoſe evils, the Parliament would care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provide for, as appertaining to ſelf preſervation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Such an attempt would be very unſafe and full of danger, were there any occaſion or appearance of need for ſuch an undertaking, yea, it would be a very raſh and impolitick courſe, and prudence would forbid it; the experience of all ages may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us how perillous a thing it is to go about to innovate or make an alteration in Government: and how much better it is for a people to bear with many inconveniences in a ſetled State, then to run upon the miſchiefs that uſually and almoſt inevitably attend ſuch a change. When the ten Tribes revolted from under <hi>Rehoboams.</hi> Government, for the burthenſomneſs of his fathers reign, and becauſe his was threatened to be more heavy; they got no caſe nor other advantage by that revolt, but (together with the loſs of their Religion and their God) they involved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſea of miſeries, never enjoyed any good Government,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115380:6"/>but through many changes, and at laſt by revolting, from under <hi>Shalmaneſer</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> they brought themſelves to utter ruine.</p>
                  <p>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>ly, What ever power of taking away and new forming Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is conceived to reſt in the People, yet it is all one as to us our Oaths, Vows, Proteſtation, and Covenant conſidered, by which we have faſt bound our hands from the uſe of ſuch a Freedom (were there any ſuch orginally reſiding in us,) theſe Oaths and Covenants which we have taken are to us far more reſtringent and ſtrongly engaging to keep to our preſent Government, then any ſecular reſpects can be to put on a change, in as much as the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of thoſe conduceth to the good or peace of the Soul &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; the proſecution of theſe reflecteth only upon a temporary Commodity. If the People of this Land, that are within any of theſe religious bonds, ſhall attempt either wholy to take away the King, the Houſe of Lords, and the ancient Knights, Citizens, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of the Houſe of Commons, or any of them, or diminiſh any thing that is matter of power, honor, or priviledg from any of them, then when they ſwore or proteſted, inherent in them, or put any power in themſelves, which they cannot have but by ſome ſubſtraction from the Rights either of King or Parliament, how can they be clear from the great wickedneſs of perjury, or Vow-violation? So that theſe Vows, Oaths, and Covenants being upon us (as we beleeve all are upon many, and ſome at leſt upon moſt of the people of this Kingdom) if this Agreement ſhall indeed be carryed on, and rendered to us, each of us (that are within any of them) may anſwer to the offer of it in the words of <hi>Jephthah, Judg.</hi> 11.35. <hi>I have opened my mouth unto the Lord, and I cannot go back.</hi> Let but the nature of an Oath be weighed, In ſwearing we call God for a record upon our ſouls, and appeal to him to be a witneſs and judg of our truth and reallity in the Oath, by manifeſting himſelf either in mercy, or judgment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as we either with ſincere or treacherous intentions under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and according as we either firmly keep or perfidiouſly break the Oath: and dare any of us be ſuch God-contemners, and ſelf-deſtroyers, as wittingly, or purpoſely, to violate our Oaths? If any unrighteouſneſs or ſin had born the ſubject of theſe Vows, Oaths, and Covenants, we might be allowed, yea bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and revocation of them that were ſuch, but no ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115380:6"/>thing hath been or can be once alledged againſt any of them: We wonder that the Framers of this Agreement are in it ſo liberal in providing for the liberty of Conſcience (as they term it) in matter of Religion, and yet are ſo ſilent in the reſolution of Conſcience in this point of Religion, which is publique enough for them to take notice of, and may (we beleeve) concern their, as well as our conſciences. Say there were ſome inconveniences (though we finde none in the ſubſtantials of our Government) yet we, having devoted our ſelves thus unto it, cannot alter any thing expreſt in theſe Engagements, without impiety, to be abhorred. <hi>A righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man ſweareth to his own hurt, and changeth not, Pſa.</hi> 15.4. The League which <hi>Joſhua</hi> made with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and the Princes of the Congregation ſware to, though it proved to be to the publique loſs and prejudice, they might not break, and they anſwered the Congregation that murmured againſt them for it, thus, <hi>We have ſworn unto them by the Lord God of Iſrael, now therefore we may not touch them: We will even let them live, lest wrath be upon us, becauſe of the Oath which we ſware unto them, Joſh.</hi> 9, 15, &amp;c. And when <hi>Saul,</hi> four hundred years after this, <hi>in his zeal to the children of Iſrael and Judah, had ſlain the Gibeonites, there was a famine in the days of David three years (Saul</hi> being dead) <hi>for that his bloody fact; and ſeven of Sauls ſons were hanged up before the Lord, ere God was entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Land,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. God hath heard our Vows<note n="o" place="margin">Pſa. 61.5.</note>, and though men do not inſiſt on, or would diſcharge us of them, yet the Lord our God will ſurely require them of us<note n="p" place="margin">Deut. 23.21.</note>: <hi>A falſe Oath</hi> is one of the ſpecial things that <hi>he hateth</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Zech. 8.17.</note>. He hath ſaid, <hi>he will come near to men in judgment,</hi> and will be a ſwift witneſs againſt falſe ſwearers<note n="r" place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> being made by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> to ſwear fealty to him, though he was a forreign and heatheniſh Prince, and though the ſubjection was diſadvantageous to him, and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>make the Kingdom baſe, that it might not lift up it ſelf;</hi> yet <hi>Zedekiah</hi> breaking this Oath, and rebelling againſt <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> the Lord ſent his Prophet with theſe tydings; <hi>Shall he prosper? Shall he eſcape that doth ſuch things? Or ſhall he break the Covenant and be delivered?</hi> Nay, upon this his breach of Oath, the Lord himſelf ſwears thus, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, ſurely in the place where the King dwelleth that made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115380:7"/>him King, whoſe Oath he despiſed, and whoſe Covenant he brake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even with him in the midst of Babylon he ſhall die; neither ſhall Pharoah with his mighty Army, and great company, make for him: Seeing he despiſed the Oath by breaking the Covenant, when lo he had given his hand, and hath done all theſe things, he ſhall not eſcape: Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, As I live, ſunely mine Oath that he hath despiſed, and my Covenant that he hath broken, even it will I recompouce upon his own head</hi>
                     <note n="(s)" place="margin">Ezek. 17.12.</note>. And again, when <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> the Princes, and people of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> had made a Covenant before the Lord in his houſe, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim Liberty, and let their Hebrew ſervants go out free, after their ſeven years ſervice, according to the Law and Covenant of the Lord, and had done accordingly; but afterwards, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the King of <hi>Babylons</hi> Army from them, they had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their ſervants, whom they had ſet at liberty, to return, and brought them again into ſubjection, the Prophet thus denounceth againſt them from the Lord, <hi>Therefore, thus ſaith the Lord, ye have not hearkened unto me, in proclaiming liberty every one to his brother, and every man to his neighbor; behold I proclaim a liberty for you, ſaith the Lord, to the ſword, to the pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and to the famine; and I will make you to be removed into all the Kingdoms of the earth: and I will give the men that have tranſgreſſed my Covenant, which have not performed the words of the Covenant which they had made before me; I will even give them into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of them that ſeek their life, and their dead bodies ſhall be for meat to the fowls of the heavens, and to the beaſts of the earth</hi>
                     <note n="(t)" place="margin">Jerem. 34.17 &amp;c.</note>. Now in this our caſe (which with the inverſion of the terms may be paralel'd to theirs) if we, having covenanted ſubjection to the Authority ſet over us, when we were in fears and dangers, ſhall, when our fears are over, caſt off that ſubjection, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim to our ſelves liberty from it, and preſume to abrogate the Government we have covenanted to preſerve, we provoke the Lord to paſs the ſame ſentence upon us.</p>
                  <p>They that hold forth this Agreement to us, ſay, in Title, it is <hi>an Agreement for a ſecure and preſent Peace, upon Grounds of common Right, Freedom and Safety.</hi> But by this Scripture, we know not how otherwiſe to ſtile it, then an Agreement for ſure and (it may probably be) preſent trouble and miſery: and if it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115380:7"/>go on to be a National Compact indeed, we doing the ſame things with <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and his people, if we have ears to hear, we may hear the Lord pronouncing the ſame things upon us which he did upon them; <hi>Behold I proclaim a liberty for you, ſaith the Lord, to the ſword, to the pestilence, and to the famine.</hi> This is the Freedom, and not that which the Agreement ſpeaks of, which we ſhall purchaſe by it: And we earneſtly with that we may not put the Lord to it, as thoſe rebellious Jews did, when he ſaid of them,<note place="margin">Jerem. 44.28</note> 
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.28. <hi>And all the remnant of Judah ſhall know, whoſe word ſhall ſtand, mine or theirs.</hi> And as for common Right, which is another thing the Title of the Book holds forth, we may gather what Right we may expect by it, ſhould it be eſtabliſh'd, by our Covenant-breaking; if we look into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophet, to wit, <hi>Hoſea,</hi> cap. 10.4. <hi>They have ſpoken words,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſea 10.4.</note> 
                     <hi>ſwearing falſly in making a Covenant; thus judgment ſpringeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.</hi> When we look into the tendency of this Agreement, and withal obſerve the poſture in which it is publiſhed, before it a <hi>Petition</hi> to the honorable the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and behinde it a <hi>Declaration</hi> to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> in both which it is with plauſible terms and Rhetorical inſinuations flouriſhed over and ſet forth; we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and make bold to put in mind all perſons, named or concerned in it, of that flying roul in <hi>Zechariahs</hi> Viſion, the length whereof is twenty cubits, and the bredth thereof ten cubits, and the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it is thus given by the Angel, <hi>This is the curſe that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth; for every one that ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall be cut off as on this ſide, according to it, and every one that ſweareth ſhall be cut off as on that ſide, according to it. I will bring it forth, ſaith the Lord of hostes, and it ſhall enter into the houſe of the theef, and into the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly by my name; and it ſhall remain in the midſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it, with the timber thereof, and the ſtones there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi>
                     <note n="v" place="margin">Zech. 5.2, 3, 4</note>. And let the ſpreading of this roul, and the pronouncing of this curſe, warn and deter us all, that thoſe very hands which were lift up to the moſt high God, in our ſwearing to preſerve the Government we are under, be not lift up againſt, or made inſtruments to pull it down, leſt we involve our ſelves thereby in the large, laſting, and conſuming curſe of the roul which the Lord of hoſtes undertakes to bring forth, and execute
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115380:8"/>upon every one where ever, upon the face of the whole earth, that doth ſuch a thing; ſo that if we fall under this guilt, <hi>though we ſhould make a Covenant with Death, and an Agreement with Hell, it ſhall not ſtand; but when the overflowing ſcourge paſſeth through, we ſhall be troden down by it</hi>
                     <note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 28.15, 18</note>.</p>
                  <p>And here, having ſo much inſiſted on the ſtrongly obliging force of our Oaths and Covenants taken, we cannot refrain our ſelves from expreſſing a little, what great heavineſs and continual ſorrow we have in our hearts for the little care that's taken by the people generally of theſe their Oaths and Covenants, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prevaricating and departing of many from the ſeveral en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors engaged to, in them, upon any temptation, either of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage offered, or danger and trouble threatened, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſneſs, backwardneſs, and indifferency of ſpirit in all (we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe not our ſelves in this) in relation to the duties of them. But eſpecially we know not how to hide or hold in the ſorrow and ſhame that, even unto horror, hath filled our hearts and faces, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of the late proceedings, both thoſe againſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and impriſoned Members of Parliament, and thoſe againſt the perſon of the King deceaſed; we not knowing how to clear them from manifeſt diſloyalty and breach of Covenant, and when we would comfort our ſelves with this, that our ſouls have not come into the ſecrets of, or been united in any ſociety with thoſe actions, but ever abhorred them; our hearts are yet faint with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, when we conſider, how, upon theſe proceedings, our Chriſtian and Proteſtant profeſſion, the Way, and common Cauſe we have ſtood for, the endeavored Reformation, and the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Covenant, we with others have entered into, are reproached: <hi>Oh tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in the ſtreets of Askelon, leſt the daughters of the Philiſtins rejoyce,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sam. 1.20.</note> 
                     <hi>leſt the daughters of the uncircumciſed triumph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But having delivered our ſenſe in this firſt part of the whole frame, and general drift of the book, we proceed to that which we propoſed for our ſecond part; the examination of the nineth Section of this Agreement, which concerneth Religion; we have ſeen its contrivements in humane or civil matters, let us now ſee how it would deſpoſe in the matters of God; and truly in this reſpect we may ſay to the promoters of it, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpake to <hi>Ahaz.</hi> the King, <hi>Hear ye now, is it a ſmall thing for you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115380:8"/>to weary men, but will ye weary any God alſo</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſai. 7.13.</note>? In ſpeaking to this Section we ſhall 1. diſſect it, ſentence by ſentence, deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as we go, the flaws or faults we obſerve in it; 2. Lay down ſome of our Reaſons againſt what we take to be the main import or project of it, to wit, the diſſettlement and free intermixture of Religion. This Section of Religion is divided into four heads, whereof we ſhall examine particularly the three firſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is intended,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Agreem. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>that Christian Religion be held forth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended as the publike Profeſſion in this Nation.</hi> 1. How reſervedly, ſparingly, fearfully doth this Agreement own Religion? as if it were jealous of engaging men to it, it dare not injoyn, no nor reſolve firmly on it, only it adventures to intend it; a word that enacts, or puts not anything in being, imports nothing but a waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing irreſolvedneſs and mutability. 2. How doubtfully doth it hold forth Religion? Here's no reſtriction to true Chriſtian Religion, although there are ſo many, &amp; ſo extreamly differing ways of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which aſſume the title of Chriſtian; yea inſtead of ſuch a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary reſtriction here's a plain implication, (in that only Popery and Prelacy are excepted from being thus held forth,) That any Religion (Popery and Prelacy excluded) may be the publique Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. 3. How pretendedly and meerly in ſhew doth it hold forth the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion? for in the three following Heads it leaves practiſe free, and what groſs hypocriſie is this? If a man ſhould propound to himſelf, and declare to others that he would profeſs Chriſtian Religion, but he would leave himſelf a freedom to practiſe any way, live as his liſt, were not this in him the moſt deliberate, wilful and perfect hypocriſie that can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined? And is it not ſo in a Nation? yet this is the Agreements Profeſſion. 4. Is not <hi>this holding forth of Chriſtian Religion as the publique Profeſſion</hi> being compared with the reſt of this Section, a ſelf-contradiction? for if <hi>none ſhal be compelled to the publique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> but may caſt it off if they will, as in the ſecond Head; and if men may both profeſs and practiſe differently from that which (it's ſaid) ſhall be publiquely held forth, as in the third Head; if this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty be generally made uſe of, what becomes of the publique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion? how is it held forth? and by whom? And ſuppoſe it not grown to that, yet this Agreement neither tells us who it intends ſhall hold it forth, nor by what acts or means it ſhall be held forth;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115380:9"/>but on the contrary, denies the Repreſentatives <hi>to have the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and final Judgment concerning things Spiritual or Evangeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 14. part. 8</note> and conſequently it cannot be done by them and for a Church Repreſentative, or National Synod, or any other way of holding forth a publique Profeſſion, here is not the leaſt ſillable, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe proviſions that make it morally impoſſible to be done.</p>
                  <p>Agreem. <hi>Which we deſire may by the grace of God he reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the greateſt purity, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, according to the Word of God.</hi> 1. Here are none nominated, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, or authorized to take this work in hand, and we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Repreſentatives, being not to have <hi>the judgment of things Spiritual of Evangelical,</hi> are diſ-enabled to do, or ſet others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. 2. But in the three following Heads there are full pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that men may (if they will) live unreformed, yea lay aſide the very face and profeſſion of Religion, or deform the Church of God in Doctrine, Worſhip or Diſcipline, without controul. 3. We have Covenanted a Reformation in all theſe; but is this hollow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, with long actual grants of the contrary following it, all the keeping and performing of our Covenant that is intended? It is no marvel thoſe words are left out [according to the example of the beſt reformed Churches,] for ſuch a Reformation is this, is without example or pattern in any Church or age. 4. It is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation according to the Word of God, That the Magiſtrate ſuppreſs the preaching of falſe doctrines, and exerciſe of falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that he command men to ſerve the Lord, according to his own inſtitution, and bring men to the means of their Salvation, which the following particulars deny him power to do.</p>
                  <p>Agreem. <hi>The inſtructing of the people whereunto in a publique way, (ſo it be not cumpulſive,) as alſo the maintaining of able Teachers for that end, and for the confutation or diſcovery of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Error, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound doctrine, is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be provided for by our Repreſentatives.</hi> 1. Here is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of able Teachers for the inſtructing of the people in Chriſtian Religion, but not a word of a Church or Miniſtry for this, or for the building up of thoſe that are inſtructed, or for the offering up of the publique Worſhip, the adminiſtration of the Sacraments and Diſcipline: Muſt we have none of theſe things provided for? Muſt they be laid aſide, until that faint deſire, without hands or endeavors, work out a Reformation? Or muſt theſe be diſpenſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115380:9"/>by any body? Here then is a Chriſtian Religion without Church, Miniſtry, Sacraments or Diſcipline. 2. Here is confutation and diſcovery of Hereſie, &amp;c ſpoken of, but no Church Cenſures, or Authority placed in any to purge them out of the Church. 3. Here is compulſive inſtruction prohibited; the meaning of which we take to be, that none ſhall be compelled to repair to the publique meetings for inſtruction, or to behave themſelves orderly therein; ſo that neither Magiſtrate, parent or maſter ſhall bring thoſe under them to the means of their ſalvation, but give them the reins to run on in ignorance, and all damnable ways. This one clauſe, if followed, is a leſſon that may more inſtruct men to irreligion and informedneſs, and more unteach men the Chriſtian Religion, then all the able Teachers, here allowed to be provided for by the Repreſentatives, can prevail to inſtruct them to it. 4. Here is not ſo much care taken to promote the Religion, which is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed publiquely to be held forth, as there is of giving advantage to other ways differing from it in the following Heads; for here the inſtruction of people unto the publique Religion, and providing Teachers for that end, is put off, and referred to the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; but the liberty of diſerting it, and both profeſſing, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing contrary to it, is preſently granted and enacted; and the Laws, Statutes and Ordinances, contrary to that liberty, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The maintenance of which Teachers may be out of a publique Treaſury, and we deſire not by Tythes.</hi> For this, we being in hand with matter of Religion, and this being but of a temporal concernment, and that our own, we ſhall not inſiſt on it: We ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to ſuffer in ſuch things, and think it but ſuitable when our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf is thus dealt with, as in this Agreement; only ſeeing that in this very page it ſaith, <hi>No Repreſentative ſhall in any miſe level mens eſtates, deſtroy property, &amp;c.</hi> We mind it, to ſee that it agree with it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Provided, That Popery and Prelacy he not hold forth as the publique way on profeſſion in this Nation.</hi> 1. They are ſo much the more beholding to this Agreement, the ways that are not thus held forth being better provided for, as we ſhall ſee preſently. 2. Then, any or all other ways of Religion, called Chriſtian, are, or may, be held forth as the publique way or profeſsion, beſides Popery and Prelacy, here then is a profeſsion of Religion of a wide
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115380:10"/>latitude, and of ſtrange party-coloured, and jarring compoſure, more like to the mixture of the cup in the hand of the great Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> or to the many headed and homed beaſt ſhe ſits on, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. then to pure and uniform Religion of the chaſte Spouſe of Chriſt. 3. Why are theſe two only excepted, is it becauſe theſe are the worſt of all? doubtleſs there are other doctrines and ways that are held forth among us, or may be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as bad as the worſt points of Popery, &amp; ten thouſand times worſe then Prelacy, ſuch as theſe of the <hi>Antiſcripturiſts, Antitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, Arrians, Pelagians, &amp;c.</hi> 4. Why are they only exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from being the publique profeſsion? If they may be allowed to be profeſſed and practiſed, why may they not be comprehended under the notion of the publique profeſsion, as well, at leaſt, as ſome other differing ways? It they be too dangerous or noxious for that notion, why are they not wholly exterminated? they may hurt as well, if they be permitted, as private profeſsion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That to the publique Profeſſion ſo held forth none be compelled by penalties,<note place="margin">2 Head.</note> or otherwiſe, but only may be endeavored to be won by ſound doctrine, and the example of a good Converſation.</hi> 1. To the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion none among us have been or are deſired to be compelled, but it hath been, and ſtill is judged, a neceſſary courſe to cauſe men that profeſs the Chriſtian Religion to carry towards it anſwerably, to bring men to the means of the knowledg of it, and to reſtrain men from publique ſcandalizing of it. 2. Compulſion by Penalties, or otherwiſe here forbidden, may include the Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures of the Church, the exerciſe of the power of parents over their children, and of maſters over their ſervants, in reference to duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the rather, becauſe it is ſaid, they only may be endeavored to be won by ſound doctrine, &amp;c. which words are excluſive of all other ways. 3. Here then (if this ſhould ſtand) men might become Atheiſts, Recuſants, Sabbath-breakers, Blaſphemers, or what they will, and no man ſay to them, what doſt thou? The former Court connivance of Popery, the prelatical indulgence of prophaneneſs, the Kings book for ſports on the Lords Day ſo much cryed out upon ſince this Parliament, were but ſmall Gnats to the ſwallowing down of this; a horrible thing to be enacted in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſo generally chriſtianized as this is. 4. Them may no Court or Magiſtrate conſtrain men to take an oath (ſuch as is uſed among
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115380:10"/>us) becauſe in ſo doing he profeſſeth Chriſtian Religion. 5. How ſhould men be won to Chriſtian Religion by ſound doctrine, and good Converſation, when no proviſion is made to bring, or keep doctrine to be ſound, and converſation to be religious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ſuch as profeſs faith in God by Jeſus Christ (however differing in judgment from she Doctrine,<note place="margin">3 Head.</note> Worſhip, or Diſcipline, publiquely held forth as aforeſaid,) ſhall not be reſtrained from, but ſhall be protected in the profeſſion of their faith, and exerciſe of Religion, according to their conſcience.</hi> 1. Thus all the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies, Doctrines of Devils, Idolatrous, Superſtitious, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Religions that ever have been broached, or pracliſed, or can be deviſed (if the perſons owning them will but profeſs faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt) are ſet a liberty in this Kingdom; nay not only granted a Toleration, but enfranchiſement, yea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and patronage, and that in groſs, without conſidering or knowing what is ſo allowed, and taken into Tutelage. 2. Although here is a diſtinction uſed betwixt the Doctrine, Worſhip and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline publiquely held forth, and other ways differing from them, yet the deſerters of, and contrary profeſſors and practiſers to the publique profeſſion have as much favor granted them (as to ſecure practiſe) as they have that embrace it, nay more. 1. None are forbidden to compel by penalties, or otherwiſe, to any profeſſion of Faith, or exerciſe of Religion, that is differing from the publique, how groſs ſoever it be in it ſelf, or oppoſite to it, only men may not be compelled to the publique. 2. None are prohibited to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain any from the publique Religion, only men may not reſtrain from the Heterodox, or differing ways, though never ſo corrupt. 3. No protection is granted to thoſe of the publique profeſſion; men may thruſt themſelves into the publique Aſſemblies, violate the Ordinances of them, and no remedy for it; men may profeſs the publique Religion at their perils, but the differing ways muſt be protected. 3. It were much more to the honor of the Name and Faith or God, if this liberty muſt be afforded, that men might have it without profeſſing Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, for the worſt the world will verbally profeſs thus much to obtain ſuch a liberty if they have need of it, and by their profeſſing thus, when as both their real prefeſſion, and their practiſe denyeth, oppoſeth and reproacheth the Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, the Name of God and of Chriſt and the true Faith are but the more blaſphemed and vilified.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115380:11"/>
                  <p>Agreem. <hi>In any place (exept ſuch as ſhall be ſet and apart for the publique worſhip, where we provide not for them unleſs they have leave.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. As you provide not for them, ſo you prohibit them not the place of the publique Worſhip, but rather by adding that reſervation, <hi>unleſs they have leave,</hi> you make them capable of it, only they muſt carry favor with them that can give leave, and then ask and have.</p>
                  <p>2. If they (to wit, the diſſenters from the publique, and advancers of another different profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) may have leave, and upon it enjoy the places of publique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, then may they by encreaſing their number come to juſtle out the publique profeſſion, and then that which in the firſt head was propounded to be held forth and recommended, ceaſeth to be the publique profeſsion, and inſtead of being held forth, is put forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doors.</p>
                  <p>3. Were this a real exeption, and might not be remitted by leave, yet it is little or no abatement of the liberty, or preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the growth of a way to e denyed the publique, if it may have free paſſage in any other place, yea if it find followers enough (as, if it be bad enough, it is likely to do) it may become as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique as that which hath that name, it being the concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not the place which makes any action of ſociety pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
                  <p>Agreem. <hi>So as they abuſe not this liberty to the civil injury of others, or to actual diſturbance of the publique peace on their parts.</hi> Civil injury then of men, and breach of outward wordly peace, muſt by all means be prevented, and rather Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined then it incurred, ſuch miſcarriages may nullifie this liberty, but ſpiritual, yea divine injury, the diſturbance of the Churches, and conſciences peace and wealth muſt be let paſs, yea protected.</p>
                  <p>Agreem. <hi>Nevertheleſs it is not intended to be hereby provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that this liberty ſhall neceſſarily extend to Popery or Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> This clauſe (as the former) would make a countenance of being an exception, but indeed is none; for as it doth not ſay, that theſe two ſhall be excluded from this liberty, ſo it leaves it Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that it may extend to them, and conſequently leaves no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in any to reſtrain them from it; if any in the place of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy ſhould go about to abridg them of this liberty, they might ſoon plead, where is your authority? The Agreement pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits to <hi>us,</hi> but never any Law forbade a thing in theſe terms, <hi>it ſhall not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115380:11"/>neceſſarily be.</hi> The ſame, though it be not expreſt, muſt needs be granted of all other ways, to which this liberty is intended; it is not neceſſary it ſhould extend to this or that, becauſe it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that this or that ſhould be.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe the exceptions that we have noted by the way, upon looking into them, appear to us to be of no reallity at all, but may be inſerted as colours and ſhadows to blind the eyes of men eaſie of belief, and to make them think thoſe more generally diſtaſted and exploded ways <hi>Popery and Prelacy</hi> are quite caſhier'd from having freedom, and that others are much confined by excluſion from the <hi>places ſet apart for the publique profeſſion.</hi> We ſhall yet further give notice to the Reader, that theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed exceptions (as to that purpoſe) are but void and frivolous terms, meer nothing, and that notwithſtanding them, Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy ſtand as free to be practiſed as any other different ways, and thoſe other different ways are as capable (if they can but get head or favor) of the publique places, yea of the ſtile of being <hi>held forth as the publique profeſſion in the Nation,</hi> as any one that may ſeem at this day to have the property thereof. For I. The ſecond and third particulars of this Section are <hi>pag.</hi> 27. and 28. declared to be <hi>fundamental to our Common Right, Liberty and Safety,</hi> and there being nothing poſitive in them to exclude either Popery or Prelacy from liberty and protection therein provided, or any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways from the publique places, (as hath been noted) they ſtand inviolably by this Agreement entitled thereunto, and in caſe any Repreſentative ſhould take in hand to reſtrain them, they may lawfully by force of arms make reſiſtance againſt the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, <hi>pag.</hi> 27. <hi>part.</hi> 10 of this Agreement; yea this being a fundamental, all they that joyn in and ſubſcribe the Agreement, bind themſelves to maintain them in it, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. 2. Suppoſe there were ſomething in theſe ſeeming exceptions, yet it vaniſheth into nothing; for if the Papiſts, Prelatiſts, or any other, do exceed them, none can take cognizance of it, or offer to reduce them into the limits of theſe exceptions, for all Repreſentatives are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the higheſt and final judgment in Spiritual or Evangelical things, and of ſo, then all other Judicatories and Magiſtrates muſt needs be denyed ſubortinate judgment or cognizance of ſuch things, under which all the aberrations in this matter are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, yea, and by this means any other Religion that cannot
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115380:12"/>be ſhrowded under a <hi>Profeſſion of Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as Judaiſm, Turciſm, Paganiſm, may yet ſettle it ſelf, and enjoy freedom amongſt us by this Agreement, if it err only in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Evangelical things, in as much as there is none that hath power of judgment over it to ſuppreſs it. We have but a word or two more way of obſervation on this Section of Religion.</p>
                  <p>We cannot but take notice, that the <hi>holding forth and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of Chriſtian Religion, as the publique profeſſion in this Nation, is laid down,</hi> not as fundamental to our Common Right, Liberty and Safety, but only <hi>as uſeful and good for the publique, pag.</hi> 28. whereas the ſecond and third particulars (wherein Liberty from the profeſsion of that Chriſtian Religion, and for a different profeſsion and practiſe from it is provided for) are laid down as <hi>fundamental to our Common Right, Freedom and Safety,</hi> ſo that by this Agreement, Chriſrtian Religion, as to the Foundation of a Kingdom, is a <hi>ſtone ſet at naught by theſe builders,</hi> though it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be <hi>the head of the corner;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 4.11.</note> whilſt Liberty to deſert that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and poſitively to profeſs and practiſe in oppoſition to it, Liberty of Irreligion, Idolatry, Superſtition, Blaſphemy, Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking, Seduction, Schiſm, is of the Foundation, ſure the edifice muſt needs be a <hi>Babel,</hi> or confuſion, a principal part of the Foundation whereof is ſuch a Liberty as this; it muſt needs be a rotten building, where Liberty to fundamental Erroe is of the Foundation.</p>
                  <p>Once more, it is ſaid, as you ſee noted, that this <hi>Liberty is fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental to our Common Right, Freedom and Safery;</hi> but let us ask what equity there is in a liberty to iniquity? In a liberty to diſhonor and injure, the Name, Truth and Ordinances of God, to infect and deſtroy the Church of Chriſt, and the ſouls of men? What freedom is it wander and run a whoring from God, to be led captive by ignorance, error and unrighteouſneſs? And what ſafety is there to open the fold for <hi>grievous wolves</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in, and devour the flock, to give way to the poyſonous and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gangrene of damnable hereſie, to ſpread without any corraſive? And was it noted of <hi>Iſrael. Judg.</hi> 5.8. They choſe new gods, then was War in the gates?</p>
                  <p>In the laſt we come to lay down Arguments or Reaſons, ſome of many (that might be inſiſted on) againſt the relaxation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115380:12"/>or ſetting free of men to Atheiſm, and the full liberty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection granted to falſe Doctrines and Religions by this Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in this Section.</p>
                  <p>1. If the Scriptures may be our rule and judg in this matter (and to thoſe that admit of their binding authority and deciſion we only addreſs our ſelves) the ſinfulneſs of ſuch a Toleration, and maintenance of erroneous and irreligious ways, wil clearly appear; 1. By teſtimonies our of the Old Teſtament, wherein there is more found for our direction, becauſe (as we apprehend it) the Governors of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to whom the Oracles of God were then committed, had in this caſe received the knowledg and worſhip of the true God.</p>
                  <p>1. By the Commandments which the Lord gave for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Idolatry, and the puniſhing of Idolaters, Blaſpemers, and Sabbath-breakers, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.5.12.2, 3.13.1, 2. <hi>to the end.</hi> 17.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Jud.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.20.31.14. <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 26, 27. <hi>Num.</hi> 15.35.</p>
                  <p>2. By the approved &amp; binding examples of the people of God, and of godly Magiſtrates aboliſhing and deſtroying the monuments and means of Idolatry, and executing puniſhments upon Idol-Prieſts and Worſhippers, blaſphemers of the living God and profaners of the Sabbath, and commanding and cauſing thoſe under their authority to abandon ſuperſtition, and to embrace the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.35.2, 3, 4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.28.1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.40. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10, 11, 24.2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.2, 3, 4, 5.15.8, 12, 13, 16.19.4. 23.17.29.5, <hi>to the end.</hi> 30.5, 6, 12.31.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 34.3, <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; verſ.</hi> 32, 33.35.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c. Ezra</hi> 10.5, 7, 8. <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.9, 11, 17, 19. Yea Gentile Princes, being convinced of their duty to the true God, have ſtraily enjoyned his honor and ſervice, and mulcted the contrary, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.3, to 13.7.13, to 27. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29.</p>
                  <p>3. By condemning and reproving the Toleration of corrupt ways of Religion, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.33. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.8.</p>
                  <p>4. By predictions and precepts (apperataining to the times of the Goſpel) holding forth the duty of thoſe that are in civil pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to promote Religion, and to puniſh the corrupters thereof by that their power, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.29. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.3.</p>
                  <p>And whereas ſome except againſt the validity of thoſe precepts, preſidents, &amp;c. as proper to the Paedagogy of the Law and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not binding to us now under the Goſpel,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115380:13"/>we ſay to that, 1. Some of thoſe commands and practices were antecedent to the Law given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as that of <hi>Abraham, commanding his children,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note> and his houſhold after him, to keep the way of the Lord:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 35.2.</note> and that of <hi>Jacob,</hi> requiring not only his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, but all that were with him (amongſt whom it is ſuppoſed were the captive <hi>Shechemites</hi> taken, in the Chapter preceding,<note place="margin">Divines Annot. in loc.</note> by the ſons of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who indeed were likelieſt to harbor Idols) <hi>to put away the ſtrange gods that were among them:</hi> And it is very remarkable, that before any Law was given by <hi>Moſes</hi> for the puniſhing of Blaſphemers and Sabbath-breakers, yet the people of Iſrael apprehended, and put in ward, both the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.12. and the Sabbath-breaker, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.34. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the minde of the Lord might be ſhewed them, having ſo much in them by the light of nature, and the rules of the moral Law they were acquainted with, that ſuch were to be puniſhed. 2. We have no other Inſtitution of Magiſtracy under the Goſpel then that which was before, nor find we in the new Teſtament any abrogation or alteration of what was before time cómitted to the Magiſtrate, but civil authority continues Gods Ordinance by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that appointment from the beginning; neither is any thing detracted from his commiſſion that was at firſt in it. 3. No Reaſon can be aſſigned, why thoſe evils in Religon ſhould be then puniſhed, and not now; they are no leſs ſins now, then they were then; they are as diſhonorable, and hateful to God, and as baneful to the ſouls of men, now, as they were then. The Reaſons given for their puniſhment then (as that they are very enſnaring if allowed to be among the ſervants of God, <hi>Iud.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.12, 13. that they tended to <hi>turn men away from the Lord their God,</hi> and to thruſt them out of his way, and that to puniſh them is to <hi>put the evil away from the people,</hi> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that all <hi>Iſrael may hear and fear, and do no more ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, Deut.</hi> 13.5, 11.) they are moral, and ſtill obtain ſtrength: Error and falſe Religion have not loſt their enſnaring nature, nor are men now more wiſe and ſtedfaſt in the truth then they have been. 4. What is now <hi>fundamental to common right, liberty, and ſafety,</hi> was ſo in thoſe former days, and we may not think that the Lord would have given ſuch ſtrict and ſtanding Laws to his people, in matters of Religion, if liberty therein had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed fundamental to common right, freedom and ſafety, as this Agreement pretendeth.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115380:13"/>
                  <p>2. By authorities out of the New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>1. The deſcription of the Magiſtrates power and duty extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the procurement of good, and avengement of evil indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely without any reſtriction; and there being no limitation of this good, and evil, in this or any other text, we muſt needs hold to that approved rule of interpreting Scripture, which is not to diſtinguiſh, or limit the ſence, when the holy Ghoſt doth not.</p>
                  <p>2. The duty of Chriſtians, in relation to their Rulers, is, <hi>to pray for them,</hi> (to wit, for their Coverſion,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1, 2</note> as appears by <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4) that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty: A Chriſtian Magiſtrate then as ſuch (and conſequently by the power of his Magiſtracy) is to aſſiſt, and promote, not only honeſty and juſtice towards man, but godlineſs and piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</p>
                  <p>3. Parents and Maſters of Families, whoſe power is of the ſame nature (that is, civil and external) with that of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,<note place="margin">2 Joh. v. 10.</note> they are enjoyned to exclude and expel <hi>out of their houſes falſe Teachers,</hi> and then by Analogy, or proportion, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are to proſecute ſuch, and exterminate them out of their ſtate. No Reaſon can be yeelded why the leſs extenſive and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior power ſhould be thus tyed, and impowered, to oppoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and not the larger and ſuperior of the Magiſtrate: only the Apoſtle might forbear to mention it of the Magiſtrates, they being at that time generally unchriſtian.</p>
                  <p>4. The Holy Ghoſt foretelleth, that thoſe <hi>ten Kings which do firſt give their power and ſtrength unto the beast, and do make war with the Lamb, being overcome by him,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.12, 13, 14, 16</note> ſhall hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and ſhall burn her with fire;</hi> that is, ſhall deſtroy the <hi>Roman Antichriſt, or Rome Antichriſtian;</hi> and that not only as <hi>the beast,</hi> having civil dominion, but as <hi>the great Whore,</hi> (that is) <hi>as a corrupter of Religion, by lyes and idolatry;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5</note> 
                     <hi>and a ſeducer of the Kings and inhabiters of the earth to her falſe Religion:</hi> But how ſhall they lawfully do this, if Kings and States have no ſword, power, or duty to command, enforce, and puniſh, in the cauſe of Religion.</p>
                  <p>3. Having thus (we hope) ſufficiently confirmed the unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantableneſs of ſuch a manumiſſion, and protection of irreligion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115380:14"/>falſe doctrine, and perverſe ways, by Scripture authority, we ſhall for a cloſe tender to conſideration:</p>
                  <p>1. How can thoſe Caveats, given us by <hi>our bleſſed Saviour, and his Apoſtles,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 7.15.</note> 
                     <hi>To beware of falſe Prophets; To take heed and beware of the leaven of the Phariſees,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 16 6</note> 
                     <hi>and of the Sadduces; To mark them which cauſe diviſions,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
                     <hi>and offences, contrary to the doctrine received,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 1.9.</note> 
                     <hi>and to avoyd them: If any man preach any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>then that we have received, to Anathematize him: To beware of dogs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 John. 5.21.</note> 
                     <hi>evil workers, and of the conciſion: To keep our ſelves from Idols:</hi> and many others How can the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the practice of theſe, and a ſubſcription, and grant of ſuch a liberty, conſiſt together?</p>
                  <p>2. How can we do this, and yet be true to our Covenant, wherein we ſtand bounden <hi>ſincerely, really and constantly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor, in our ſeveral places and callings,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Artic. 1, &amp; 2.</note> 
                     <hi>the Reformation of Religion, in the Kingdoms of England, and Ireland, in doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government: To bring the Churches of God, in the three Kingdoms, to the neereſt Conjunction and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Religion, Confeſſion of Faith, Form of Church-Government, and Catechiſing; That we ſhall in like manner, without respect of perſons, endeavor the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Profaneſs, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>even ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. In doing this thing ſhall we not fail, deſert, and give up that Cauſe for which defenſive Arms were taken up by the Parliament and Kingdom; for the maintenance of which ſo many lives have been adventured, ſo much blood hath been ſpilt, ſuch miſeries have been waded through in the late Wars, yea, ſo many prayers put up, and Faſts publique and private obſerved, <hi>one main</hi> (if not the firſt and principal) part of which Cauſe was <hi>the Vindication and Defence of Religion?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See Declarat. of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, 1643.</note> And ſhall we thus improve and requite all the wonderful ſucceſſes and deliverances wherewith the Lord of hoſtes hath owned, and pleaded this Cauſe for us, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our deſires therein?</p>
                  <p>4. What advantage would this liberty give to our, and religions enemies, to open their mouthes in reproaches, &amp; blaſphemy againſt our way; who have formerly objected againſt us, That our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne was to promote private fancies, to introduce a multiformity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115380:18"/> of Religion, and to ſubvert Magiſtracy; and whom we have charged with <hi>a cup filled up to the brim of Apostacy, Atheiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Decla. of both Kingdoms. p. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Idolatry, Blasphemies; and Profaneſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. Shall we not aſperſe all the petal Laws of the Land, and all the judicial proceedings that have been upon them ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Seminary Prieſts, Jeſuits, and Papiſts, or any other, juſtly ſuffering in matter of Religion, as acts of higheſt injuſtice, being againſt <hi>the Fundamentals of common Right, Freedom, and Safety?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Will not this Liberty, reduced into practice, be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, not only to deface, defile, rend, and crumble to nothing our Churches, but to fill the Kingdom full of Factions and Tumults, and tend to the overthrow of the Magiſtrates power in civil things, and that men having once got head, and immunity in the things of God, will proceed to introduce a lawleſneſs and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in humane Intereſts; the Commandments of both Tables be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo united and enwreathed in one, that they ſtand and full to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin">Iames 2.10.</note> and the violation of one hath an influence upon all; and it being ſo eaſie for men willing to err, to entitle any civil extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy, not only to Conſcience, but to Faith and Religion?</p>
                  <p>We have thus, in the uprightneſs of our hearts, delivered our Judgment concerning this Agreement, and Subſcription to it, not affecting Diviſion, or Faction, but vehemently deſiring and ſeeking a religious Peace, and right agreement of the people; not intending any diſreſpective reflexion upon the perſons of any, but heartily deſiring the true honor and happineſs of all; and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring, according to our places, to prevent the great evils that we pre-apprehend will enſue, if this Agreement ſhould be carried on. As for us, <hi>we ſhall not</hi> (we truſt) <hi>ſin against the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12 23.</note> 
                     <hi>in ceaſing to pray for you</hi> our dear Flocks, and the reſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt in theſe Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that he would direct your courſe in this caſe of ſo weighty and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental an importance: <hi>and we have herein endeavored to ſhew you the good and the right way:</hi> And having layd before you thoſe Grounds upon which <hi>we profeſs our diſagreement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Book</hi> called <hi>the Agreement of the People:</hi> We teſtifie the ſame by underwriting our names.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Heyrick</hi> Warden of <hi>Chriſts
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115380:19"/>Colledg</hi> in <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Hollinworth</hi> Fellow of the ſaid Colledg.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Walker</hi> Miniſter there.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alexander Horrocks</hi> Miniſter in the <hi>Dean</hi> pariſh.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Tilſley</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Dean.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Alt</hi> Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel at <hi>Bury.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Toby Forneſs.</hi> Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel at <hi>Bury.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Bathe</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Rachdale.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Hyet</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Croſton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Ward</hi> Min. of the Goſpel at <hi>Walton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Johnſon</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Halſal.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Woolmer</hi> Min. of <hi>Flixton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Cranage</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Brindle.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Wood</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Aſshton</hi> in <hi>Makerfield.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Fleetwood</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Kirkam.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Angier</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Denton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Pyke</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Radcliff.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115380:19"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Harriſon</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Aſshton-underline.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jonathan Scholefield</hi> Min. at <hi>Heywood</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Holland</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Ringley.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Conſtantine</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Oldham.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Meek</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Salford.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Walton</hi> Min. <hi>of Blakely.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>David Durie</hi> Preacher at <hi>Gorton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Walker</hi> Preacher of the Word.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Joanes</hi> Min. at <hi>Hool.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Henry Welſh</hi> Min. of Gods Word at <hi>Chorley.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Crompton</hi> Min. at <hi>Aſtley.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Peter Bradſhaw</hi> Min. at <hi>Cockey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſaac Ambroſe</hi> paſtor of <hi>Preſton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>James Bradſhaw</hi> paſtor of the Church at <hi>Wigan.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Fogge</hi> paſtor <hi>of Liverpool.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Maudſley</hi> paſtor at <hi>Ellens.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Yates</hi> paſtor at <hi>Warrington.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VVilliam Dun</hi> Min. <hi>of Ormeskirk.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Norman</hi> paſtor at <hi>Newton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115380:20"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Paul Latham</hi> paſtor <hi>of Standiſh.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VVilliam Leigh</hi> paſtor at <hi>Newchurch</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VVill: Garner</hi> preacher of the Goſpel</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas VVhitehead</hi> paſtor at <hi>Halton</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Shaw</hi> Min. at <hi>Cockeram.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Gee</hi> paſtor at <hi>Eccleſton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VVill: Brownſword</hi> paſtor at <hi>Douglas.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chriſtopher Edmundſon</hi> paſtor at <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtang.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Peter Atkinſon</hi> Min. at <hi>Ellel.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard VValker</hi> Min. at <hi>VVarton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VVilliam Smith</hi> Min. at <hi>Overkolles.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Seddon</hi> min. of the Goſpel at <hi>Alker.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Cunningham</hi> preacher at <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Fiſher</hi> paſtor at <hi>Biſpham.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Jaques</hi> paſtor <hi>of Bolton.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Syll</hi> paſtor <hi>of Greſsingham.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John Harper</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Rich. Goodwin</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list> Miniſters of the Goſpel at Bolton in the Moors.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>March 6. 1648.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Imprimatur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JOHN DOWNAME.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115380:14"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>
                     <hi>additions of grace and glory into Gods Children,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 2.10.</note> and therefore the chief marks of Gods favour: As in our gracious King <hi>Charles,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 12.10.</note> who was alſo <hi>taken away from the evill to come,</hi> in Gods mercy unto him; which thou even thou, unto the ſhame and confuſion of thy face (although thou haſt harned it) ſhalt ſee in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching day of <hi>Englands</hi> calamity, which in a great part is procured and haſtned <hi>by thy infernall counſels;</hi> thou needſt not to have given that Scripture ſuch a violent ſtretch ſo to ſtreine it as to make it reach from <hi>Aſſyria</hi> unto <hi>England,</hi> or to travaile ſo farre for a reaſon <hi>why His Majeſty ſhould not have a royall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with His Maunceſters;</hi> the cauſes were nearer thee, Let me aſſigne them:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it had been a Condemnation of your ſelves to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him ſolemne and Kingly Funeralls, unto whom you gave ſo unjuſt and cruell a death, that were <hi>to build up what you were reſolved to deſtroy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next, you could not but know, that the neighbourhood of his ſacred earthly remaines muſt needs refricate the ſcarce skinn'd ſorrowes of <hi>London;</hi> when they ſhould have ſuch a ſtanding and ſtill preſent Monument of their former happineſſes, in His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties peaceable Government; and of their new miſery in your Tyranny, which would ſerve alſo (this being the place of the greateſt confluence) to recrude the griefe of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and probably beget ſuch compunction and reluctancy in both city and Kingdome, as would teſtifie it ſelfe, by their attempt to caſt you downe headlong from your new and wickedly acquired Dominion.</p>
                  <p>Another reaſon was, leſt the nearneſſe of his Body whom you murthered, might too frequently offer unto you the horror of your Guilt, and redouble unto you thoſe inward cheques and laſhings of your Conſciences (which you cannot be without) and ſo impede and trouble your Counſels.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Devill</hi> at the <hi>Oracle of Apollo of Daphne</hi> could not give his Anſwers unto <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theod. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> who ſent to conſult him about his undertakings againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſo long as the body of the <hi>Martyr Babylas</hi> lay by him, ſo it is to be preſumed that the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> (which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>powerfully worketh in the Children of Diſobedience</hi>) might be hindred in his cooperation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115380:15"/>and influence upon thoſe unto whom he hath conſigned the chief exerciſe of his power in our Engliſh world, if King <hi>Charles</hi> his ſacred reliques were lodged ſo nigh unto them as <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and therefore <hi>Windſor</hi> was neare enough.</p>
                  <p>But from the view of <hi>His Majeſties undeniable matchleſſe Virtues,</hi> let us paſſe unto that <hi>of His Sufferings:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sinfull <hi>envie</hi> never failes to give a malitious attendance upon <hi>virtue,</hi> which by how much the more it is illuſtrious, with ſo much the greater <hi>rancour</hi> doth ſhe dog and perſecute it, and therefore <hi>many are the troubles of the righteous;</hi> and no (meer) man had ever more, then righteous King <hi>Charles:</hi> behold and ſee if any ſorrows and ſufferings were like unto His. See one of the moſt potent <hi>Monarchs of Europe,</hi> loved at home, and feated abroad, moſt injuriouſly and ſtrictly Impriſoned, debarred from the moſt deare ſociety of the moſt virtuous and beſt Wife, from the converſe and ſight of his moſt ſweet and hopefull Children, from the attendance of his moſt faithfull Servants, from Gods houſe, from Gods publique worſhip &amp; all Gods Servants, fore'd to cohabite with Beaſts, brutiſh, ſavage, and wicked Men, &amp; theſe to be made the Inſtruments of their cruelty unto him, who were his ſworne Subjects and Servants, upon whom all civill and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine obligations of duty and affection unto His Majeſty reſted, and that upon <hi>pretenſions of Religion and Liberty,</hi> of which <hi>He was the trueſt and moſt undoubted Defender;</hi> to lie under the weight &amp; wounds of ſo many ſcandals, reproaches, wants, and miſeries; beſides the moſt grievous ſenſe of the ſufferings of his Kingdoms and beſt Subjects, to be daily tortured with ſo many iterated, unreaſonable Propoſitions, and inſolent Demands, to be racked out of his undoubted Royal Rights, to make ſo many Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions &amp; ſuch great Condeſcentions in his propenſneſs unto peace, which notwithſtanding his Enemies never meant; to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (if it wre poſſible) unto <hi>perjury, ſacriledge, and Acheiſme;</hi> and to have no other Conditions propounded for the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Crownes and Kingdomes, then that which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill made unto our Saviour, <hi>All theſe will I give thee if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me;</hi> to offer his owne (that which never was theirs) to deny God, which God gave him to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and worſhip him: Theſe muſt needs be ſorrowes and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115380:15"/>as beyond expreſſion, ſo above our conception; moſt terrible teſts, and trials of all his virtues; certainly no man had ever more, and more ſtrict examinations of Gods graces in him, all which he fully anſwered with a learned and invincible piecy; for in all theſe who ever heard him murmure, repine, or <hi>charge God fooliſhly?</hi> who ever heard him accuſe, raile at, or threaten his moſt confirmed Foes? with <hi>Job,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 16.20.</note> 
                     <hi>his eyes ſtill powred out tears unto God,</hi> whoſe juſtice in their greateſt injuſtice he acknowledged, and although he vindicated his owne Innocency, <hi>(having where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to juſtifie himſelfe before man)</hi> from theirs; yet <hi>not before God,</hi> he cleared the equity of his judgement upon him, for <hi>acting againſt his Conſcience in the Earle of</hi> Straffords <hi>death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it was the great and crying guilt of theſe Nations ſinnes (<hi>Englands</hi> principally) which made this righteous man <hi>fall into the pits</hi> of his Adverſaries, to ripen Gods judgement upon this Nation, by that great addition of guilt <hi>[the ſhedding of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud]</hi> who had ſo many characters of Gods ſupreme power and ſpirituall graces upon him, as muſt needs make this Crime committed againſt God, and draw his ſpeedy and unavoidable vengeance upon them for it.</p>
                  <p>God uſually puniſheth one ſinne by ſuffering Sinners to fall into others, and thoſe cuſtomary ſinnes accompanied with ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſſe and impenitency, which fills up <hi>the meaſure of ſin</hi> brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for judgment to take it off: ſo that this pious Prince fell in the very <hi>conruption of Chriſtianity,</hi> which is of farre more maligne aſpect, and hath a more malitious influence of impiety upon the actions of men then Atheiſme it ſelfe, for then men profeſſe <hi>that they know God, jet in their works they deny him;</hi> uſing the name of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> as Conjurers int heir Incantations to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate thoſe things are moſt contrary unto God, and deſtructive unto Religion; for as the Devill never doth more hurt then when he appeares <hi>in the likeneſſe of an Angel of light;</hi> ſo are men never ſo miſchievous, as when they drive on wicked deſignes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>ſhew of Godlineſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Englands</hi> former ſins which cauſed this Gods juſt dereliction, &amp; the abandoning them up unto greater, were their <hi>exceeding lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xury,</hi> in <hi>turning the grace of God</hi> (temporal favours) <hi>into wantonnes,</hi> the long continuance of their peace, the increaſe of their Trade,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115380:16"/>riches, and plenty, begot in them a generall inſolency and pride, ſo that when <hi>they Waxed fat,</hi> like <hi>Jeſurun, they kicked againſt God,</hi> in the Authority and regard due unto his principall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, the <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſt:</hi> Hence the people of <hi>England</hi> (in their generality) became <hi>ſelf-willed, heady, high-minded,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible, they <hi>ſlandered the footſteps of Gods Anointed, ſmote him-with the tongue, contended with Gods Prieſts;</hi> and uſurped that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Juriſdiction which God had delegated unto them, as thoſe Conſpirators did (<hi>Ye take too much upon you ye Sonnes of</hi> Levi, <hi>ſince all the people of the Lord are holy</hi>) under pretence of then Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the Clergy; and being like <hi>Elihu's now bottels,</hi> ready to burſt, with that liquor or flatuous and ſuperficiall knowledge inſtilled into them by the giddy preachments, and undigeſted, ſwelling, and tedious prayers of <hi>their Lecturers,</hi> (who reduced all Religion unto lip-worſhip, and canting Scriptures.) Hence came it to paſſe that contemning the old paths, the truth of the <hi>reformation</hi> in the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> they contended <hi>unto bloud</hi> to corrupt by their phanatick Alterations, the pure <hi>Doctrine</hi> &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical <hi>diſcipline</hi> eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to effect which with the more eaſe, <hi>they</hi> adventure upon <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> to carry on that, they muſt pull down <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> (the <hi>fence of the Church</hi>) and here the <hi>King,</hi> as <hi>a nurſing Father</hi> interpoſing, they tender Him unable by encroaching upon his Prerogatives, quarrelling him, ſeize upon his Strengths, Arme, fight againſt him, Impriſon, and then <hi>Murther Him;</hi> which <hi>laſt Act of Rebellion,</hi> though the greateſt part of the firſt Engagers may be thought never to have intended, yet they may ſee the firſt violation of their Obedience due unto His Majeſty puniſhed, by a guilt (thus farre) of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, bloud, that that power which they raiſed, <hi>ſpilt it;</hi> So dangerous it is to vary from a Chriſtian Principle, or <hi>to doe evill that good may come of it,</hi> God onely having power to direct, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and determine any evill action: ſo that looke over the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree of <hi>Englands</hi> ſinnes through the ſeverall deſcents thereof, and you will find it thus, <hi>peace</hi> begot <hi>wealth,</hi> that <hi>plenty,</hi> that <hi>pride,</hi> that <hi>vanity,</hi> that <hi>curioſity,</hi> that <hi>contention,</hi> that <hi>hate of the Clergy,</hi> that <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> that <hi>the downfall of Biſhops,</hi> that <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the</hi> KING, that <hi>Warre,</hi> that <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and that the <hi>murther of the King,</hi> a <hi>murther,</hi> the moſt horrid murther that ever
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115380:16"/>the Sun ſaw, for Subjects to take away their KING's life; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the preſcription of a ſingle example, or a law; nay, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all lawes divine and humance, to Trie him after the forme of a Judiciary proceeding, this is to entitle God unto the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinne; <hi>to establiſh iniquity by a Law,</hi> and to make God ſuch as themſelves: Thus the <hi>Jewes</hi> dealt with our Saviour,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.7.</note> 
                     <hi>We have a Law, and by that Law he ought to die, becauſe he made himſelf the Son of God,</hi> although there was no ſuch Law; but a new-made Law, a <hi>Junto</hi>-law, <hi>Straffords</hi> law, <hi>Canterburies</hi> law, the KING's law (conſequent Lawes, Lawes without names or cognizance) made becauſe He was KING. Neither doth their Power any more prove the equity of this fact (the great ſcandall of the Chriſtian name, and height of Anabaptiſtical fury) then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils power (which is from God) doth juſtifie his malice (which is from himſelf.)</p>
                  <p>They have now indeed made King <hi>Charles</hi> a Glorious King, prov'd him glorious in his Perſonall virtues, glorious in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, but moſt Glorious in the Chriſtian Conſtancy of his Glorious <hi>ſufferings for Gods Cauſe, the true Proteſtant Religion, and the Lawes and Liberties of the three Kingdomes,</hi> thus hath God extorted a <hi>truth</hi> from them; <hi>for this ſpake they not of themſelves, but</hi> (God forceing their teſtimony) <hi>they prophecyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As we have ſeen His Majeſties <hi>ſufferings,</hi> and their <hi>cauſes</hi> our ſins, ſo let us reflect upon their <hi>puniſhment;</hi> as the Springs from which our <hi>ſorrowes</hi> ſhould ariſe.<note place="margin">l'it. Conſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
                     </note> The exceeding <hi>avarice</hi> and <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie</hi> (two noted Court ſinnes with which the greateſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was abuſed) of the State-Grandees, <hi>the deep pits</hi> wherein they laid the fatall ſnares into which pious King <hi>CHARLES</hi> fell, will be viſibly puniſhed, for <hi>God will not be mocked.</hi> The <hi>pride, vanity, ſacriledge, rebellion,</hi> and the <hi>cruell murther</hi> of <hi>His Majeſty</hi> will have particular judgements levell'd againſt theſe ſinnes; every mans ſinne even of thoſe who have fought for His Majeſty who have yet fought againſt him by their ſinnes hath given force unto this great ſtroked and wound given unto theſe Kingdomes in His Majeſties death; and therefore ought every man to proportion his ſorrow unto his ſinnes. As King <hi>Joſiah</hi> from <hi>Judah,</hi> ſo the ſtrong Barricadoe King <hi>Charles</hi> is taken away betwixt Gods judgements, and this Kingdome, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115380:17"/>great and wide Inlet of all miſery is made by his death, could our ſorrows anſwer them, like a Torrent, it would over flow all the banks of reaſon, and grow too big to be carried away by the chanels of our ſenſes: behold every ſpring of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahs</hi> ſorrow open, to ſend forth theſe flowing ſtreames of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction upon us, and alſo ariſe from the ſame head; <hi>The breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord was taken in their pice, of whom we ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder his ſhadow we ſhall live among the Heathen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe heavie judgements which the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> foreſaw impending, and after came to paſſe by King <hi>Joſiahs</hi> death, are in agreat part by King <hi>Charles</hi> his death,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.10. &amp; 2.7.</note> already come upon us. Gods houſe his beautifull houſe <hi>is laid maſte, the Heathen have entred into the Sanctuary, they have made a noiſe in the houſe of the Lord as in the day of a ſolemus Feaſt:</hi> So that they who in the beginning pretended <hi>God, Religion, the Church, [their Cauſe]</hi> have dealt with us as that Faction among the Jewes who called themſelves <hi>The Zealous in the Warre with</hi> Titus <hi>did under pretense of defending Religion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſeph. Bell. Jud.l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and the Law, they poſſeſſed themſelves of the Temple, yet were themſelves the firſt who put fire with their owne hands into the holy places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How hath the avarice and carnall intereſts of the Teachers of theſe times corrupted the purity of our Religion,<note place="margin">Lam. 2.14.</note> as <hi>Judahs,</hi> ſo <hi>Englands</hi> onely <hi>Prophets have ſeen vaine and fooliſh things for her, and they have not diſcovered her iniquity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4.13.</note> 
                     <hi>to turne away her capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ene for her falſe burthens and cauſes of baniſhment; they have ſhed the bloud of the juſt</hi> (K. Charles) <hi>in the midſt of her.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1.5.</note> Englands <hi>greateſt Adverſaries are chief,<note place="margin">5.8.</note> and her Enemies proſper; Servants doe beare rule over us, and there is none to deliver us out of their hand.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4.5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They that did feed delicately are deſolate in the ſtreets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">5.12.</note> 
                     <hi>they that were brought up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear let embrace dunghils. Princes are hanged by their hands, and the faces of the Elders are not honoured. Warre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation,</hi> and <hi>famine,</hi> with their ſad effects, foretold in theſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, appeare in our Horriſon already like <hi>Elijahs</hi> little Cloud, which will ſhortly overſpread our whole Engliſh firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and all theſe calamities have and will fall upon us,<note place="margin">5.16.</note> becauſe <hi>the Crowne is fulne from our Head;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1.9.</note> the Brittiſh <hi>Joſiah</hi> K. <hi>Charles</hi> is taken from us, and we have <hi>no Comforter;</hi> and how great and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115380:17"/>juſt Cauſes of our ſorrowes are all theſe Calamities: But let this ſorrow have the full advantage in its fall, (to adde motion unto all the turning wheels of our afflicting griefs) the fall from our great happineſſe in His Majeſties Government: Let <hi>London,</hi> let <hi>England,</hi> let <hi>Scotland,</hi> let <hi>Ireland,</hi> let every of them <hi>Remember</hi> (as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did) <hi>in the daies of her afflictions and her miſeries,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>all the pleaſant things that ſhe had in the daies of old.</hi> All the pleaſant things they had in the bleſſed daies of King <hi>Charles</hi> his bleſſed Reigne, <hi>the glory and truth of her Religion,</hi> the juſt execution of her <hi>Lawes,</hi> her <hi>peace,</hi> her <hi>riches,</hi> her <hi>plenty,</hi> her <hi>liberty</hi> at home, and her <hi>protection and honour</hi> abroad,<note place="margin">2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>England</hi> was <hi>the perfection of beauty, and the joy of the while earth. The Kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world would not have believed that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary and Enemy ſhould have entred into the Gates of</hi> (our) <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, London,</hi> that Churches ſhould be turned into ſtables, Gods Houſes made Coures of Guands, the Royall Palaces made Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Tythes (the portion of Gods Miniſters) made the Soldiers ſalary, that the Law ſhould be <hi>turned into wormwood,</hi> our Religion and, Liberty meaſured out unto us by the Pikus length, the Deciſions of the Sword become the Principles of Faith, and that (:which is the Cauſe of all this) mechanique Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Trades men (who will certainly marre, never can mend ſo great concernments, they never before handled, or were acquain-with) the ſole Moderators of Publique affaires, and the chiefe Princes and Potentates of our Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>But now <hi>the glory is departed from</hi> (our) Iſrael,<note place="margin">1.1.</note> 
                     <hi>the Arke of God is taken,</hi> and how is <hi>England become a Widow?</hi> made a prey unto cruell people, and skilfull to deſtroy, who daily force and proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute her unto their wicked purpoſes: for theſe things let <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (and every true-hearted Engliſh-man) ſay, I <hi>I weep,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1.16.</note> 
                     <hi>mine eye, mine eye runneth downe with water, becauſe the Comforter</hi> (King <hi>CHARLES</hi>) <hi>that ſhould relieve my ſoule, is farre from me. The breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>life</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> of our <hi>Lawes,</hi> of our <hi>Liberties,</hi> is taken from us; the <hi>Image</hi> of Gods power in ſupreme Authority, Indemnity, &amp; Inviolability, is taken from us, our <hi>Phyſition,</hi> our <hi>nurſing Father,</hi> our <hi>Comforter,</hi> our <hi>Protectour, is taken from us,</hi> and for our ſins was <hi>taken in their pits,</hi> ſo that now we want the <hi>Wings</hi> of his <hi>protection</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115380:18"/>among theſe <hi>Heathen</hi> among whom we live; we are now made very Slaves unto the worſt of Heathen, a People without God, without Faith, without Law, without Rule, without Reaſon, without Humanity, without all theſe, and whoſe unrully <hi>will</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is unto them all theſe. Theſe calamities are all fallen upon us, becauſe <hi>The breath of our Noſtrils, &amp;c.</hi> pious King <hi>Charles</hi> is taken from us like <hi>Elias in a fiery Charriot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vit. Conſt. l. 4. c. 73.</note> (or as <hi>Conctantine the Great</hi> after his death was impreſſed on a Coyne pluck'd up by a divine hand) <hi>into Heaven, that his eyes might not ſee, nor his righteous ſoule be afflicted with all that evill which is to come upon us, to conſume us;</hi> woe unto us for we have ſinned. Theſe are but the contracted heads of thoſe miſeries which we ſhall all read over, in the vaſt volumes of our approaching woes; and juſtly beſpeaks ſuch ſorrows as might transforme us into <hi>Niobes,</hi> make our <hi>heads ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of ſorrowes, and our eyes fountaines for continuall teares.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lond in mercy looke upon us, and wipe away theſe teares from our eyes, and their Cauſes, our ſinnes from our ſoules; and ſince <hi>the bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church,</hi> in mercy unto his Church reſtore the ſeed of his Martyr King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt unto the Government of theſe Kingdomes, that Religion, Peace, and Liberty, may be reſtored unto us: I conclude theſe ours,<note place="margin">Lam. 5.21, 22.</note> at the Prophet doth his Lamentation, <hi>Turne thou unto us, ô Lord, and we ſhall be turned; renew our daies as of old, if thou hast not utterly rejected us:</hi> heare our prayers O Lord for thy Sonnes ſake, unto whom with the Holy Ghoſt be aſcribed, &amp;c.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
